A Guide to the Additional Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean 1860-1950
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean 1860-1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1331-b
This collection consists of 810 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Jefferson Randolph Kean Papers were loaned to the Library by Mr. Jefferson Randolph Kean of Springfield, Virginia, on June 12, 1985.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of General Jefferson Randolph Kean (1860-1950) contains ca. 810 items (2 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet), 1906-1950, chiefly correspondence, 1906-1944, papers generated by Kean's involvement with the Association of Military Surgeons, 1914-1934, and the United States Territorial Expansion Memorial Commission and its successor, the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial Commission, 1934-1950. The collection also includes four bound letterpress copybooks of Kean's outgoing letters, and a microfilm copy of Kean's autobiography, from the original placed in the National Library of Medicine. The individual correspondent files include three Surgeons General of the United States Army: Merritte Weber Ireland (1867-1952), William Crawford Gorgas (1854-1920), and Robert Maitland O'Reilly (1845-1912); and, John J. Moran and William H. Taft. Letters from Moran concern the yellow fever experiments in Cuba and include one, July 31, 1937, mentioning the interest of Philip S. Hench in the experiments. Correspondence with Taft concerns a recommendation for Surgeon-General and Kean's appointment as director of military relief for the American Red Cross during World War I. The papers relating to the Association of Military Surgeons include: correspondence, annual meetings, constitution, and by-laws, membership, and miscellaneous material.
Organization
This collection is divided into four series: 1) Papers of J.R. Kean, 2) Papers re United States Territorial Expansion Commission, 3) Letterpress Copy Books, and 4) the Autobiography of J.R. Kean. The organization established by the donor has been maintained.
Contents List
- Series I: The Papers of J.R. Kean
  - Kean, J.R., Letters from M.W. Ireland 1906 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Letters to M.W. Ireland 1906-1907 (Box 1)
  - Station List, Army of Cuban Pacification 1907 Jan (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Letters from M.W. Ireland (6 folders) 1907 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Correspondence with General R.M. O'Reilly 1907-1909 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Miscellaneous Correspondence While in Cuba 1907-1909 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Correspondence with W.C. Gorgas, and a letter about Gorgas 1913-1917 (Box 1)
  - Taft, W.H., Correspondence with and about J.R. Kean 1913-1917 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Letters sent, While in France (3 folders) 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Letters received, While in France 1918-1919 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Correspondence with J.J. Moran 1928-1944 (Box 1)
  - Kean, J.R., Association of Military Surgeons, Correspondence (6 folders) 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - Association of Military Surgeons, Annual Meetings 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - Association of Military Surgeons, Constitution and By-Laws 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - Association of Military Surgeons, Membership 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - Association of Military Surgeons, Miscellaneous Papers 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - Kean, J.R., Association of Military Surgeons, Correspondence (2 folders) 1924-1928,1934 (Box 2)
- Series II: U.S. Territorial Expansion Commission
  - Meeting of the U.S. Territorial Expansion Memorial Commission - Minutes (2 copies) 1934 Dec 19
  - Jefferson National Expansion Memorial - Progress Report 1940 May
  - Jefferson National Expansion Memorial - Reports 1950 May
  - Jefferson National Expansion Memorial - Papers 1945-1950
- Series III: Bound Letterpress Copy Books
  - Volume IV 1909 Feb-1910 Sep
  - Volume V 1910 Sep-1911 Dec
  - Volume VI 1911 Dec-1913 Apr
  - Volume VII 1913 Apr-Jun
- Series IV: J.R. Kean's Autobiography
  - 1 Reel of microfilm from the original in the National Library of Medicine n.d.